[Music]
you
hey guys so we are joined by Mike and UV
of the future thinkers podcast and it's
probably overdue to be honest that we
connect because we're in very similar
areas we speak to a lot of the same
people I'm really interested to hear
from you guys what you've learned from
those conversations and how that's
influenced what you're doing because I
know that there's probably quite similar
journeys and yeah I'm really intrigued
to hear how that's been and maybe if you
could just start by introducing
yourselves and how you feel that you're
the future thinkers podcast has evolved
over the last few years since you
started doing it sure and likewise it's
we've been very intrigued by what you
guys are doing and it's been actually
really nice and refreshing to see you
putting out this content I think there's
a huge necessity for it
so yeah I honestly think that the the
more of the these conversations are out
there the better because they need to be
happening so as far as future thinkers
goes we started in 2013 in the end of
2013 we recorded our first episode and
it started because Mike and I were just
having interesting conversations with
each other every morning over coffee and
we had a bunch of friends who had
podcasts they were mostly business
podcasts but we thought why not start
our own podcast but that wasn't about
business it was just about us you know
talking philosophy with each other
navel-gazing philosophy yeah and we'd
actually kind of started off doing this
digital Nomad thing we read that book
4-hour workweek and kind of use that as
a road map for running a business
traveling and we we left bought one-way
tickets to Thailand in 2013 and then you
know we'd so it sold Tim Ferriss is both
it is really but we were interested in a
lot of the subjects you know the
philosophical psychedelic kind of you
know those weird navel-gazing subjects
so we ended up having a lot of those
conversations when we had kind of bought
our time back through being digital
nomads so read a lot more books had a
lot
or those conversations then decided to
start recording them did you guys do you
guys have like a background in
philosophy or anything you study at
university but what brought you did that
specifically we both had actually quite
a series of really challenging events
happening kind of in our late teens
early 20s a lot of deaths around us a
lot of just really challenging things
and for me I'll speak about myself it
kind of got me into meditation and and I
started to you know realize the
fragility of life and got into a lot
more philosophical subjects there's a
lot of the stuff I'd been doing at that
time was a lot more related to just
music and music production I was trying
to be a recording engineer and so I I
just felt like I wanted to have some
kind of bigger impact than just
recording metal bands and in a basement
studio and I wanted to travel and see
the world and that kind of stuff so that
really started the adventure for me I
grew up in during the collapse of the
Soviet Union so I think just seeing the
grit of the world and the problems of
the world just shoved right in my face
from an early childhood made me question
a lot of things made me question reality
question why you know people on TV were
saying one thing but I was seeing
another thing in my everyday life and so
I just I spent a lot of time alone I was
kind of a loner as a kid and just spent
a lot of time thinking about nature of
reality I didn't develop a formal
meditation practice until later but that
was also a big part of my path I studied
psychology and university and also
trying to understand human nature and
had you know had a lot of challenges the
same as what Mike was saying and so I
think it was just a natural progression
for both of us that we came to these
subjects okay so you both have a
background in kind of inner growth work
of some kind meditation and philosophy
so what topics do you tend to cover on
the show well it's actually kind of
blending of our two interests like I'm a
lot more techie you know study
programming engineering that kind of
stuff so I really like that stuff I was
really interested in artificial
intelligence and blah
Chane a lot of these technologies we
haven't really been covering that stuff
lately it's been more about personal
development psychology sociology we're
really interested in the development of
society and so we've been attracted to
thinkers like you know Jordan Peterson
Jordan green Hall Daniel Stockton Berger
these guys who are trying to map out the
territory of the necessity of evolving
society and so that's what our podcast
is about the evolution of technology
society and consciousness yeah yeah I'd
love to come back to that in a minute
about I think probably we've all of us
have a sense of that there's a kind of
direction to this conversation and that
we're following the thread of the
conversation and where it's going the
the kind of emergence of Jordan Peterson
was a real kind of exclamation point in
that and then and we've also I've got a
sense we've also kind of honed in on
some of the similar thinkers who we
think have the really crucial pieces to
add to that conversation
you mentioned Jordan Greenhalgh or
Jordan Hall as as he now is Daniel
Shmack Tim Berger for example Jamie
wheal those kind of thinkers who are
probably not as well known yet as the
sort of intellectual dark web thinkers
but we all think have something really
crucial to add to the conversation so
just before we get into that we'll talk
a little bit about our background so Ali
and I actually met through the
psychedelic festival breakin convention
which is the biggest festival around
psychedelic science in in the UK in
Europe as well in Europe yeah at least
that's what we say yeah I know it is the
biggest in Europe yeah yeah and so we've
had a shared interest in psychology
psychedelics personal growth and
transformation and personally I trained
as a journalist I've worked for about
probably 12 to 15 years as a journalist
at the BBC and then at channel 4 and
then started making documentaries for
the BBC in channel 4
so working inside a newsroom as well for
there's a lot of people who work make
documentaries
I think that experience of being inside
a newsroom and being like immersed in
the in the conversation for over 10
years is something that that is is quite
a unique obviously it's not unique lots
of other people do it but but it gives
you a different sense of kind of the ebb
and flow of the of the the news agenda
and just getting very frustrated and
very bored with the whole thing like how
facile so much of the conversation is
and how difficult it is to break out of
certain ways of looking at the world and
how much is excluded from those the
everyday perspectives and and what I
what I really I'm hoping for from the
the video side of rebel wisdom is that
we're bringing a slightly deeper lens on
some of those questions and I'm also
interested to see where that goes in the
future what are what would a education
policy or a health a health policy
influenced by a much deeper sense of who
we are as people rather than this sort
of materialist paradigm or this very
transactional game a if people know that
kind of terminology the terminology that
Brett weinstein Jordan Green Hall often
often use and that's something that I
think is really interesting that's what
I sort of see going forward is the
interesting area to look at if we took
it talking about systems change or the
end of one paradigm what does this new
paradigm look like and then just to sort
of round that off that has to go into
the transformational that has to go into
the liminal that has to go into the the
areas of what you might call
spirituality or personal growth or and
there's also not really a good language
for it because all of those words are
contaminate to one degree or another so
it's like how do you have the
conversation while all the terminology
that you might use to talk about it as
associations that you that
block so many people from hearing what
you have to say so yeah that's why rebel
wisdom with rebel wisdom we run events
we run live
we run live events and then
transformational workshops to try and
bring all of those pieces together yeah
my background is maybe not so different
to yours Mike in the sense I started
meditating quite early on in my life so
I think I was maybe 18 19 and I was
really I guess has been to threads my
own personal development I was one with
psychedelics which is the reason I
actually started meditating his paws I
was fascinated by that experience and
fascinated by really what what what had
opened up and so got quite into
meditation and then was fascinated by
just the whole philosophy around the
psychedelic world so I see I used to
spend lots and lots of times in forums
arguing about free will versus
determinism and any any kind of subject
and that really felt like the cutting
edge of the conversation to me maybe 15
years ago even to this day I have a
feeling that a lot of what was coming
out of the psychedelic community 20 from
you 20 years ago onwards was still very
relevant and maybe quite far ahead of
its time I see a lot of the same ideas
popping up so I got involved in well I
started with my wife a meditation school
in London and also I'm one of the
organizers of breaking convention this
psychedelic conference David mentioned
earlier which is happening now again in
August so it's been really interesting
to watch that strand grow I think over
the years I kind of took a step back
from the psychedelic world because I
feel any community gets very insular and
gets into a bubble and I didn't feel
like all of the interesting
conversations were happening there then
as well as all of that I was also
working kind of leading a double life
that was a very strange period where I
was running a meditation studio and also
freelancing and working in advertising
agencies and marketing agencies and
having a foot very much in both worlds
in the world where you have to explain
things very simply to people
and the world of inner development where
it's sometimes impossible to explain
things at all so I've always found that
intersection and that crux point really
fascinating - I think Douglas Adams said
2fd ineffable now how do you how do you
translate what really is liminal and
can't be felt in a way that is useful
for people and that people understand
and so that's that's always been a
fascination of mine and yeah and the
inner growth work which it sounds like
all of us share has been come
increasingly important not just
meditation but also group work and
practices like for example breath work
or a lot of the embodied practices have
become another piece of the puzzle so it
feels like much like covering this
conversation there's always pieces of
the puzzle that slot in and then there's
a kind of growing emerging process both
on the individual level and the
collective level as well
yeah what's fascinating to me is the
layering of all of these different kind
of disciplines and I definitely
reference spiral dynamics quite a bit
because there are so many ways and
developmental levels to look at the
world and they become your lens whatever
kind of level you're operating from and
you could look through shamanism
Buddhism the IDW all different ways of
kind of understanding the world but I'm
really interested in the connection
points between all of them the
similarities and overlap it's been
really interesting bringing integral
into the conversation with the the IDW
because obviously we have interviewed
quite a few of the IDW figures and then
talked about the IDW as an emergent
integral conversation in a piece that
Ken Wilber read and then got in touch to
say I'd love to speak to you about this
and then we did the interviews with him
and that I think Jamie will put it well
and that a lot of people who are
currently breaking trail are running an
integral OS it's a very good operating
system I think the danger with it is
that it's easy to get caught in that if
you get caught in that operating system
then suddenly you're only communicating
with other people who are inside that
system and you get lost in the map which
ironically integral talks about how you
must never get lost in the map and then
promptly often gets lost in the map but
there is this there is a sense for me
certainly that the this IDW
constellation really needs that map like
peterson obviously he talked a lot about
jean piaget and jean piaget was one of
the originators of a whole of a
developmental model but I really think I
just look at some of the conversations
that are being had for example the Sam
Harris Jordan Peterson debates about the
nature of truth and the nature of
religious truth it's like are there in
different quadrants just talking past
each other and a little bit of integral
theory would have really helped them
navigate that conversation you wouldn't
had this sense of them just talking past
each other infuriating Lee for hours on
end yeah this is so true I think it's
really interesting how something is
emerging right now where people are
starting to understand that a single
point of view is insufficient to view
the world and we need some sort of a
collective consciousness or a way to for
multiple people to contribute pieces to
create a more whole picture of what is
going on and I think that the
intellectual dark web has kind of
started on that path where they're
trying to integrate different points of
view but then they stalled a little bit
because maybe people got too famous or
you know they're getting a lot of
reinforcement for this kind of more
polarized or political stuff and they a
little bit got away from the sense
making conversation and there are other
thinkers that are now becoming more
prominent who are picking up that trail
I think that's the crux I think that's
the crux of what's going on and it's
it's it's something we've talked about a
lot and I've been wrestling with a
documentary for quite a while glittering
the matrix 3 which is about exactly this
I think the issue is partly that people
in the IDW some of them were very
attached to certain perspectives if
you've built a career on a certain
perspective it's very hard then to
unpick that and say the
with this there is a sense at the
beginning especially the way it was
originally framed as if you've got a
better idea I'm happy to change my mind
this can be an evolving conversation and
I think it's fair to say that that's not
really been borne out I don't I don't
have a sense of real novelty coming from
that constellation for quite a while now
yeah I think it's for me it's
interesting to compare the the IDW to
the thinkers we kind of touched on
earlier we've all had in channel you
know Daniel schmuck Tim Berger Jordan
Hall John reveille key who have an
attitudinal difference then many of the
IDW figures do now at least you know
maybe it wasn't true at the beginning
but the idea of being okay with not
knowing the idea of the liminal or all
of that is is so simple and yet so
hugely important for the way the
conversation moves and and so much of it
also maps on to what we know from the
meditative with the contemplative
traditions you know knowing how not to
become attached knowing the dynamics and
the phenomenology of attachment all of
these things from the upper left
quadrant let's say from the inner world
they are very important to translate
into the way we communicate with each
other and it's it's complex but I think
hugely hugely important yeah I've been
very curious of where the influences
have come from is if we want to use
Jordan Peterson as an example like to me
it felt like at the beginning my
interpretation of him was that he was
trying to be a demonstration of how to
debate properly and it seems now that
when you look at the YouTube headlines
anything to do with Jordan Peterson is
generally Jordan Peterson destroys so
and so right and so and then there's the
fame component with him as well that
he's kind of blasted in the stratosphere
of Fame and so there's something about
the controversy that has pushed him that
high that is now maybe causing him to
perpetuate some sort of controversy like
there's there's generally nothing kind
of easy about what he says it's very
like finger pointy kind of like you need
to do this you're doing this wrong that
kind of thing so it's very hard for me
to
separate him from this movement in the
way that this this movement seems to be
co-opted by this sort of clickbait II
kind of headline-grabbing
attention-grabbing oppositional exactly
so when we spoke to John Vevey key he
said that he thought it was a mistake to
to go down to the political level so
he's talking about the meaning crisis
and how Jordan Peterson success is
directly related to the meaning crisis
but he he personally would was much less
comfortable with making political
statements and bring it down into
political realm but at the same time
Jordan Pederson has a lot of his success
and a lot of his fame has been that he's
willing to have those conversations and
he's also when he's good at it he's very
good at it the the Kathy Newman
interview for example I think was a real
case in point it was he kept his cool he
seemed very it really showed up a sort
of a kind of simulated thinking in the
media really really well because it was
like she was running a program and it
was like but there was an opportunity
for a dialogue and that I thought could
have been had and I'd loved to have seen
him and Kathy for example have another
conversation I was actually can I work
with Kathy and I also had done the
documentary about Jordan I was trying
behind the scenes to get them to be able
to talk to each other but it was already
there was a lack of trust there and
Channel four News didn't want to go
there Kathy Newman didn't want to go
there Jordan did and I see so many of
the and then I I have a sense since then
that he is and he's actually talked
about this himself in one of his Q&A s
that he's felt a little bit of battle
weariness and defensiveness coming up
and I think that's probably true with a
lot of the other people in the IDW that
sam harris as well and eric Weinstein's
also said that so many of the critiques
were low-quality that they've started to
actually become immune and and death to
some of the better critiques and I think
that
it must be almost impossible if you're
at that level of Fame and you're getting
so much critique and so much of it is
actually poor to then be able to
differentiate okay what's the good stuff
from the bad stuff yeah
I'm really curious of your guys's
perspective on the kind of shift in
conversation in the IDW and namely I
think I heard this term from you guys
first the intellectual deep web why's
there a necessity to switch or what
what's with the new label I don't really
understand it how he came up with it so
what's with it yeah it's well I think
the the initial impulse was a lot of
what we're talking about now is that
okay well there's a couple of things
firstly I don't think the conversation
that needs to be had and the movement
that we need to make as individuals or
collectively is going to be solved from
the intellectual level alone I think the
intellectual level is very important but
if something gets stuck in the
intellectual it just goes round and
round and you need something I mean we
know this even from research into
creativity you know Annie McGilchrist
who you've had on the channel a few
times has got a great take on this with
the left brain and the right brain as
well the right hemisphere being largely
responsible for what we don't know and
if we're if we're not tapping into that
and we can get just kind of shut down
into reality tunnels so the intellectual
I mean to be fair the word intellectual
should be out of the entire equation I
think rather than just intellectual deep
web is just a little bit more punchy but
that that there needs to be again an
integral view on it there's the
intellect and then there's something
that goes beyond the intellect and both
of those need to be in the conversation
and rarely do I see that in the
intellectual dark web certainly not
recently at all really and that's the
missing piece I think and that's the
piece that I think we're always on the
lookout for and I think you guys to it
is is who's holding who's holding that
perspective that can contain many
perspectives and that can say I don't
know and that can let go and flow and
also that there is so I think it's also
you
to think about who who it would be in an
intellectual deep web that wouldn't be
in an intellectual dark web because I
think for me the intellectual dark web
it's it's very if it's got Jordan
Peterson in it certainly goes beyond the
purely materialist but there is still
quite a kind of materialist bias to it I
think and I I think that the other
thinkers that need to be integrated into
any sort of if what we're moving towards
is a genuine synthesis then I think we
need people like Stan Grof for example
who was doing some incredible depth
psychology with psychedelics back in the
50s and 60s came up with with some kind
of incredible models for personal
transformation and you've got people
like Richard tarnis who I think are some
of the an incredible thing put produced
something called passion of the Western
mind and then cosmos and psyche who are
the people who are just a little bit too
esoteric for a evolutionary an
evolutionary biologist like Brett
Weinstein or maths and physicists like
Eric - like who's a little bit too hot
to handle for someone who's still
concerned about their standing in the
Academy and and who had who is holding
those extra pieces
I'd say it's also the kind of esoteric
tradition of people at Rudolf Steiner
it's Carl Jung who thanks to Peterson is
now becoming part of the conversation
again but but even he was warned not to
go anywhere near Carl Jung while he was
at when he was at uni it was like this
is this is intellectually toxic to go
anywhere near him Freud just about that
no Jung is it's too far away is too too
esoteric now thankfully Jung seems to be
coming back in a really big way and I
think he's a absolutely crucial thinker
but then you've got Stan Grof who goes
even further than Jung in in many ways
so it's like who are those people
because I think there are if you look at
history as a kind of a river and a set
of eddies who are the people in the
Eddy's to the side of that main
intellectual current
that are holding really really important
pieces and I think some of those names
that I've given it are some of them and
I'm sure we can come up with more if if
we wanted to and that for me is the
depth the depth piece and also that
there's something about dark light
there's there's an implicit there's an
implicit binary and the intellectual
dark web that I think isn't so much
there with the deep web there's there's
not really a binary with depth and
shallowness in the same way as there is
with dark and light so I think we need
to get out of the binary you need to get
out of the sort of polarization and the
depth maybe the way to get out of it
I've got a question for you guys
actually on this note a lot of the
thinkers that we talk about or speak to
are thinkers you know they they're
medium let's say is ideas and
communicating those ideas usually with
language there's I'm very I'm often
wondering where are the artists and the
storytellers and they're really you know
maybe it maybe there's a sculptor who's
going to have some incredible
explanation of the meaning crisis for
example have you guys ever thought about
these people these figures have you had
any who have you had on who you would
classes kind of maybe a little bit more
out there I would one of my favorite
Benzes tool I would love to have main or
discuss these subjects he's written so
much about Carl Jung in the past
transcendence DMT experiences he's a
brilliant thinker he's boring as hell to
interview but yeah I I think that you're
really onto something and actually as
you were talking about this I was
thinking that it's exactly that what you
said it's not thinkers it's more the
practitioners who are going to become
important and we've noticed this pattern
actually in our courses that people want
to gain some sort of information some
sort of knowledge your framework but
they don't actually want to apply it and
this is a big problem with a lot of
people who hang out and kind of
intellectual in the intellectual space
that they're uncomfortable leaving it
and the kinds of people that I think we
desperately need in this new
conversation are the people who are
comfortable in or at least have
experienced the no mind no self
liminal space yeah it's a problem with
this space that a lot of these ideas
actually they can only be described
through language but you're describing
like how do you describe a DMT trip in
language it's just like it fails we try
it we did a whole series on DMT UV and I
took turns and then we would document
the experience and both of us would just
come out of the trip laughing because
it's impossible to describe it it's like
you know I was like okay I know I've got
to describe this now and then all I
could do is laugh at least you've got a
story for when you go and Joe Rogan's
podcast and he asked you the inevitable
question yeah he does a brilliant job of
explaining it I don't know how he puts
words to it practice that's right I
think there's a huge vacuum a a need for
artists to come into this conversation
and I just don't see it being filled at
all like I would love to see more
graffiti and more music and and all
kinds of different digital arts being
done and that's something I think we've
tried to do with our podcast like I
create a lot of the artwork for the pre
for the podcast before we switch to
video and it was just an attempt to
visualize the subjects right but I don't
know I don't know why there's not more
out there that's kind of more popular
than it is well I think it's that that
point that some people are just good at
practice but they're not good at putting
into words and vice versa and even in
saying that I see a huge need for
bridging it's like we need better
integration again in integral terms we
need to integrate all the different
faculties of the human experience that
have become so separated for different
cultural reasons yes there's a there's a
band that I'm really into at the moment
called comet is coming and I might even
post the link to the review of their
their latest album and it's the music is
the same story like what they're saying
through their music is exactly the same
story as I'm hearing through the the
guys on the cutting edge the Daniel SHM
Acton Berger is the Jamie wheel I think
the review said something like dancing
in a it's like it
like hopeful hopefully apocalyptic music
in some sense that what they're and what
I hear in the music and why I'm sorry so
enthused by it is this sort of a
liveness of possibility with this sort
of still sense of the overwhelm of the
of the the moment at the same time and
so I do think there are there are people
communicating very similar things in
different mediums but possibly and I'd
love to talk to the the saxophonist
about it and I I strongly suspect that
that he would be trying to communicate
through his music exactly the same
experiences probably through a lot of
the same substances as some of the some
of the guys that we're thinking about
have have also experienced and so it it
is a case of bridging though building
those bridges as you said UV how do you
build those bridges what is the
soundtrack to the kind of conversations
that we're having actually I just got
reminded there's this short film that we
really liked recently by Luba Mir our
arse off yeah is that his last name
called in shadow and it's it has a very
trippy music soundtrack and it's just
visuals it's a very beautiful kind of
dystopian demonstration of the the
fakeness of current civilization and
then at the end this hopeful twist that
is very I don't even know how to
describe it it's esoteric it's like
sarcastically optimistic somehow I
didn't find it to be sarcastic I found
it to be very kind of mystical union of
the feminine and the masculine and they
ascend and it's a very super archetypal
so I thought that was really cool it's
interesting that we we had Erik Davis
here yesterday you guys know Erik Davis
the author he kind of he's written a few
books that I keep row one called tech
gnosis which is the intersection between
technology psychedelics the esoteric a
really interesting guy but he had this
for
is that stuck with me he talked about
live we're living in a banal apocalypse
and I'm just cut it just popped up as
everyone's talking because that is a
common theme in the art that you're just
describing is there is a sense of
there's a sense of banality and a sense
of apocalyptic an apocalyptic situation
and I'm still trying to feel into that
the same question you had my cab while
he goes like why aren't there lots of
artists putting out stuff was in every
other historical period I can think of
it was the the push against the culture
were the thing that helped a new thing
emerge was driven by the artists and
interestingly now it seems not to be
driven by the artists and in fact they
seem to be absent not that they're not
there at all but it's kind of hard to
find them you know we're talking right
now we're kind of figure out that
there's this you know a few things are
tapping into it so I don't know whether
that means we're headed for an explosion
of a new era of art or something else is
going on I hope so I mean one of the our
favorite subjects to talk about is basic
income which is and the reason before I
get into that that I love that subject
so much is that I love art and I love
seeing art without the commercial means
and I think a lot of corporations are
really good at co-opting art the second
you put something really mind-blowing
creative out there someone wants to hire
you to make their explainer video you
know so Luba Mir is a good I think a
good example of this I don't know what
he's doing now but he made this
brilliant art piece and we wanted to
work with him and he's just booked up
forever there's no way to get him so
yeah I think something like a basic
income even a small amount just to get
expenses covered would be really
interesting to see the effects on the
art explosion that would happen after
that you know how many times do you ask
people what they would do you probably
asked this question at the retreats all
the time what what would you do if you
could do anything you want if my name is
not an object exactly and how many
answers do you get back that it's like
arts or music or something like that
it's like most of the time that's what
it is I'd make documentaries that kind
of thing so I would love to see what
would happen with the basic income is as
far as the art explosion goes take away
the commercial incentive yeah I wanted
to just raise something else
just thinking about that bridge building
that I was thinking maybe we talk about
after the call but let's talk about it
now and maybe it's something to be put
out there as as a kind of open inquiry
how do we turn this conversation that
we're all aware of as a kind of emergent
phenomenon and we we're all I'm sure
you're contacted by people in the same
way that we are like constantly saying
how can I get involved in this I really
recognize what it is that you guys are
doing I've been following the same kind
of threads how do we how do we turn this
into a cultural movement how do we how
do we make it into more than the sum of
its parts in a way that I mean I don't
know what that is I don't know whether
it's a it starts with a kind of dialogue
in an email thread or a Facebook group
somewhere or something and and we think
about who are the other people who are
part of this kind of emergent phenomenon
and and try and pull our resources I I
don't know what it what it is but I do
get the sense of that we I mean I
certainly feel it myself very keenly
with rebel wisdom it's like if we're not
a catalyst for something bigger than
ourselves then what are we doing this
for because we don't have time either
even if we were able to build a really
kind of and we're barely sustainable
sort of financially as it is but if we
were able to create a sort of
financially sustainable business and
we're doing really well I don't think
that's enough I don't think that's
enough for what needs to happen in the
near future and I think it has to be
some form of catalyzing something bigger
than ourselves in that way and and in
this game be world that we talk about as
well that it's about it's a trans egoic
space what does it look like to operate
in this trans agarics pace who are the
other people that are operating in it as
well and I mean really operating it and
I'm just saying that they are and then
when it comes to any could have crunch
decisions they go back to their kind of
ago--it programming how do you get
beyond this and how how do we how do we
scale or create more than how do we
create a movement around
that's my question that's why I open
inquiry I think I have three kind of
answers to that the first is what we've
attempted to do with our courses which
is about kind of about the isolation
that people you know who are writing
those emails or asking they want a
community to plug into but there's a lot
of work that needs to be done just on
your own there's a lot of meditation
there's a lot of exploration there's a
lot of deconstruction of my ego and
identity that I think is necessary to
establish what I would probably term a
collective intelligence like a global
collective intelligence there's a lot of
ways that a collective intelligence can
screw up if someone you know is
signalling how smart they are or you
know wants to be the center of attention
or is just kind of operating out of ego
so there's there's that initial thing
that people need to do before they
should even attempt anything else do
that in that self construction and
deconstruction work I think that's what
Peterson talks about quite a lot then
there's the community aspect which is
parallel which I think you guys are
trying to do as well as us so I think
that means that we need to have people
who are kind of training the trainer's
to go out there start their own thing
could be a podcast could be a
documentary could be art of any kind
we've talked about a lot of that stuff
but just start their own community where
they are so plug into online communities
like what we're doing and then start
your own thing as well so those are the
three things I would say that practice
is a huge part of it because it's not
just that people need to be having
conversations and I think that was one
of the maybe failings of the integral
movement is that it just became very
intellectual you know people are just
yeah we're all so integral and we're
having these integral conversations but
no change is actually happening so
change comes through practice and you
know accessing that liminal space where
your previous sense of self your
previous sense of the world can dissolve
so that's something new can emerge and
I think that giving people maybe a set
of practices but something that they can
do on their own without supervision
without guidance and a way to
self-organize is going to be really
useful something simple and replicable
yeah I agree with that I think there's
also a big missing piece and one of the
big reasons that it's so difficult to
get us all to go kind of post egoic and
stay there and be anti fragile in that
and not not crumble when when the stakes
get higher is that we need something
some higher order purpose which is
higher than the ego that everyone is
aimed towards and we used to have that
and I feel often in the conversation the
high level conversation there's a lot of
euphemisms for god or for the divine or
for the mystery or whatever it is and I
don't think it needs necessarily to be
named but I think you know young talked
about this as well and just in terms of
the ego in the self if the ego doesn't
have the self to sit within and the ego
thinks it's above the self then you get
the narcissus and then you get the
confusion you need something that
contextualizes the ego but I guess the
complicated thing is how do we find that
thing or what is that thing how do you
even point people towards that thing in
a way they agree to you know because
that I think is very important there
needs to be some sense of we are all
working towards some higher purpose or
just some higher and I'm not sure what
that higher purpose should be framed at
but it feels like a very important piece
that's missing because that brings
humility and it also brings shared focus
and intention mm-hmm yeah I I struggle
with that one actually to define that
for myself because I mean I have worked
really hard to to remove desire and
remove ego from as much as I can in my
day to day life I'm not saying that's a
cop that's mission accomplished but and
I think to a degree what we're doing is
future thinkers I have done it in a way
that cleans the purpose of it like we
are is I want to have fun doing what I'm
doing and I want to affect people but
beyond that the day to day if it's not
fun it's not going to be
achieved I'm not gonna do it anymore I'm
not gonna work on it if if it affects
people then that's just a byproduct and
I think the fact that that's my one of
my first priorities cleans the purpose
of it where it's like I'm not attached
to some result I don't need your money I
don't need your approval I don't need
your you know respect I just want to
have fun and share what I'm passionate
about some of these subjects that we're
talking about I think that's kind of the
same you're more Purpose Driven than I
am but but I I think removing the desire
to be something or signal something or
achieve something has really cleaned the
whole thing for me so I'm not chasing
after money I'm not chasing after
approval anything like that like I used
to but I think what Alex was saying is
that there needs to be something greater
for it to fall back on because not
everybody can just exist in that void in
that empty space like that's it's much
more difficult you know it's like a few
steps down so something greater than
yourself to rest on is a lot more
achievable for the majority of people
whether that's God or nature the mystery
or the universe the divine whatever they
call it but if people disagree on what
that is then it can cause problems in
the cream I think it also allows for for
those those kind of we talked about
branches as a metaphor yesterday like
swinging from branch to branch like a
monkey it's like you go from one
ideology and then that ideology
collapses and you have to grab on to
something else and what I'm attempting
to do is just to let go altogether and
see what happens and I think that's a
big part of the problem in this
conversation is people are operating
from their different ideologies and
trying to like co-opt other people and
or convert and I just think a lot of
that needs to stop and for us to just
you know kind of go both end like accept
all the positions and not really hold
tightly to any position and that's been
if I if I hadn't of like
go completely I think I probably will I
probably would have still been pursuing
money and that's that message and goal
of future thinkers would have been
bastardized in some way but there must
be like there must be some odd no I say
must be I'm wondering is there the in
letting go psychologically is very
difficult to do unless you feel you're
gonna be caught unless you feel that say
the universe is a fundamentally
supportive place that it's safe to let
go into and I'm wondering if that is how
you see things because I I think that's
partly what I mean by a sense of kind of
coherence and cohesion in reality that
people agree on as well it's quite
important but and that was traditionally
the role that religion would give people
for example they would know that there
is a higher order purpose there is a
there's a reason to things and that
creates a different kind of interaction
now we're well past you know we're in a
we're in post modernity so it's very
difficult to just go back to that so I
guess that that's my inquiry is what
does it look like now how you know in a
decentralized collective intelligence
what does that shared thing like I think
verve a key talks about this in probably
the most detail and says it in the best
way I think we are in a meaning crisis
and a lot of times in the past that
meaning has been given from religion of
some kind but it's also been provided by
tribes in community and I think we lack
both of those things generally and which
is why people are just so desperate you
know if you kind of let go of the
branches I think the tribe is meant to
be there to support you through that and
we don't really have that so that fall
is potentially dangerous but I think
that's that should be the goal like
establish a community establish a tribe
and then try and let go the problem that
I have with that is that people tend to
farm meme tribes they form tribes around
ideology because they desperately need a
tribe so to go back to the question of
is there some shared higher purpose well
because we are experiencing very serious
existential risks on this planet
especially climate change which is
becoming very
accelerated and very evident I think
that for the time being that shared
purpose or that something greater than
ourselves could be earth nature and I
think that's something that a lot of
people can connect with quite easily and
it's not very esoteric either what do
you guys think I can answer it for
myself I don't know if I can answer it
in the general I know what it is that
makes my life purposeful I know what my
particular skill set is and I know what
that what I have a sense of what that
there's this kind of sense of a verb
there's the Buddhist idea of awakening
but I think there's a kind of deeper
awakening which is where you awaken and
in some sense that means the universe is
way more intelligent than then he's
almost conceivable that you realize you
kind of awaken into a place where you
have exactly the right skills and the
right you awaken in exactly the right
place that we're all sort of and that's
kind of what we're all trying to express
in some in some sense like this and we
all have to find that for ourselves and
we have to find that kind of awakening
into the place where we're meant to be
with exactly the right history and
having achieved all of giving ourselves
exactly the right skills to do what we
need to do next and that's something
that we all have to come to ourselves
it's very difficult to generalize and
because when you start looking for this
grand explanation what you end up doing
is coming right back down to the level
of the individual and right back down to
the very almost the microscopic I mean
the the kind of clean your room is not a
ridiculous place to start but the
missing piece in that that I think a lot
of people react against in in Jordan
Peterson is he doesn't make the next
step like clean your room sort yourself
out first and then you'll know what to
do next and then there's that when you
break it down like that it almost sounds
like magical thinking and it and when
you expect when you explain it in that
way
sound like magical thing is what do you
mean how can that be when you look at
the the ice caps melting and the
biodiversity loss and all of these
require structures to deal with it's
like all I can do is say is trust that
all of the people who have caught been
called into making that particular area
of because I'm not I'm not a climate
scientist I don't know
anywhere near enough about all of these
things to say anything definitive I
sense that same level of existential
threat and I think that the crisis that
that is a manifestation or is far deeper
and I'm interested in the sort of
philosophical roots of that crisis and
that's what I think
I'm personally speaking to in the
interviews and documentaries that I'm
making and I know that I can do that and
that's what I think I meant to be doing
but all I can do is have faith that the
people that are that are involved in
those conversations are having similar
awakening moments to the ones that I'm
having and I see the people around me
having that that will be the thing that
gets if not all of us but at least as
many of us as possible through what is
to come does that speak to them to that
question or not yeah it does it inspired
the next train of thought here for me
which is you mentioned Peterson saying
just clean up your room and that kind of
like okay what's the next step I really
feel that what the next step is there
that and I've kind of feel the reason
he's not saying it because there is no
road map that can just be handed you you
do have to just keep kind of climbing on
your own and for a lot of people they're
they're freaked out by the state of the
world but they're you know the room
isn't clean they're in that that is a
metaphor like their life isn't clean
that they're kind of grasping onto one
thing or another and emotionally
reacting to nearly everything and
there's something about that in the way
our society converses and tries to make
decisions collectively that is is
causing a lot of problems like the
reason we can't collectivise solve some
of these problems you know
make policies that at least try and work
towards reversing climate change and
that's just one example like we're we're
just not collectivizing and having
productive conversations and I think the
IDW is attempting to show people how to
have productive conversations again so
there's something about sovereignty
individual mental sovereignty that is
important here where I feel like if you
if you're looking for meaning in these
different things like out meaning in it
as an I must contribute to the world I
must change the world and it's like you
haven't done that individual quiet work
of cleaning your room cleaning your life
then you're you're not gonna be prepared
to make the right steps in the world you
might be responding to some sort of
internal lack or fear and you're going
to be taking actions that aren't
necessarily going to be the right thing
for the world so that's why I think it's
kind of self-evident in what he's saying
what the next step will be it's like
there's so much work to be done
individually and then the path every
next step lays itself out for you as you
go and I think there's another thing
that's quite interesting about the IDW
or the intellectual deep web and it's
specifically to what Jordan green Hall
or Green Jordan Hall and Daniels Martin
Berger have been saying and not
necessarily what they're saying but how
they're saying it it's like they've
climbed this mountain this intellectual
mountain and have surveyed the landscape
surveyed the mountain that they've just
finished climbing and there's a lot the
rest of us are still climbing and we're
trying to figure out how to get there
and I'm I'm not saying there's a plateau
and it's done like there's still
climbing as well but it's like they
they've turned around in our shouting
instructions at us but those
instructions are not really helpful in
in the position that people are at
generally they don't necessarily need
the survey of the landscape they just
need to be told
keep going and this is Klima Bly mobile
you can do it like when you're climbing
you're just worried about the next step
just keep going the next footing it's
almost like they're describing the
landscape that's up up ahead but you
don't need to know that to get there
most people don't
yeah and I think that's one of the
reason Peterson's been so successful is
because he has surveyed the land and
he's not really shouting back these
detailed instructions at people he's
just saying take the next step
clean your room you know do that next
thing because people are so lost and
they're basically stuck at their base
camp and not moving so he's just saying
start climbing again start climbing well
I also want to just throw something more
in here just in case people are watching
this and haven't seen much of Peters and
stuff because you can't break down like
if you watch the maps of meaning lecture
series compared to his 12 rules for life
for example which I have to admit I
haven't finished reading the the maps of
meaning lecture series is a is an
absolute tour-de-force it's an absolute
masterpiece of a coherent in theory of
everything
similar to Ken echoes of Ken Wilber for
me and the kind of the breadth and the
attempt at linking together all of these
kind of mythologies and stories into a
coherent framework so it's not that it's
not that all he's offering is sort of
cleaning your room and do the things you
can do there is a there is a much
broader vision that that I don't think I
don't think as many people as I would
like or aware of but yeah I just wanted
to sort of throw that in there just I do
a little shout out to the maps of
meaning series yeah it was awesome
actually it's it's what got me into
Jordan Peterson as well I wanted to
speak to the sovereignty peace and I
think that it's an extremely important
process and practice coming into the
world that we're living in now and for
the future so sovereignty as in having
an internal compass having internal
authority for where you're going instead
of looking for some external person
authority figure system map to tell you
what to do anywhere to go because the
the ground is shifting beneath our feet
even the authorities or so-called
authorities don't know where they're
going they're just doing their best and
the people who seem to be making the
most sense
are in fact operating in that liminal
space where the ground is constantly
shifting underneath their feet and I
think that that is maybe the most useful
thing that people can do is find their
own internal compass so that all they
really need is for somebody to just
encourage them and say keep going and
this is doable and nothing more they
have to figure out everything else by
themselves and I know that's extremely
harsh and it doesn't land well with a
lot of people that we try to tell this
to what I really deeply think that
that's what's necessary right now and
yet if you look at the hero's journey
that that is the that is every story
it's the it's the space of going from
dependency and a lack of agency and lack
of sovereignty to having to make the
choices for yourself to decide who am i
what kind of person am i and the hero or
heroine makes those choices and then
they are someone else at the end yeah
and continuing with that metaphor there
there is usually in the hero's journey
that wise character that hands the tool
the sword the map the ring whatever to
the hero that allows them to cross cross
the threshold and achieve their goal but
it's never like a full map yeah that's
another sort of jumping off point but
I've heard it said many times where are
the elders mm-hmm yeah I our elders have
not gone through what we've gone through
they were not born into the internet
they were not born in the transition of
the Internet they're barely keeping on
you know keeping up with what's going on
and and things are moving so fast that
they'll never keep up so we're in need
of new elders like we basically have to
be that this internet generation of the
Millennials we have to kind of establish
a system in our own ranks to kind of
push people through wisdom to be the
elders for the next generation cuz we're
basically in that crossing the threshold
State there's just not no one who's
mapped this territory ahead of us barely
I mean some people are but they're
they're barely older than we are there
any anything that you guys wanted to say
before before we wrap up maybe give a
shout out to your course and the fact
that you are doing some of the you are
providing some of these tools that we've
talked about yeah sure well the the
courses can be divided into two parts
there's sovereignty so how to get
clarity in your perception your sense
making your agency there's a lot of
stuff to do with deconstruction of the
mind and that one the second part is
about shadow work which is about facing
your demons facing the shadow in the
Jungian sense which i think is pretty
much a necessity to be able to
participate in the collective
intelligence that's you know a lot of us
are trying to converse about in these
types of conversations and also to be
able to contribute meaningfully to the
world without acting out those
unconscious traumas or issues yeah that
you can find at courses dot future
thinkers org and then our podcast just
that future thinkers network yeah and
we're also planning some retreats that
are going to be probably in Bulgaria or
Portugal to start and then who knows
where else that put these things into
practice and create the in-person
community for people to be able to
participate in this work great and you
guys I know are doing these retreats
yeah I really I was hoping to talk about
that a bit well come on one and then
then you'll definitely have more to talk
about yeah well do a cultural exchange
yeah yeah the meant the men's work we
we've been doing for quite a long time
since we we set up our own men's group
found it really useful and then expanded
that out into firstly day-long workshops
and then a whole weekend based on the
hero's journey that I III genuinely
think it's about as powerful a two-day
process as there is out there having
done a lot of this kind of work for
quite a while it really it gives people
an opportunity to real opening to make
changes in their lives which is
ultimately all all we can do is create a
kind of a space for people to make the
changes because it's then up to them to
to put them into practice but it's also
in the in the retreat is about
empowering the guys to create their own
men's group to support
to each other afterwards - to use that
space - to catalyze yet to empower them
to support themselves which is all we
can do really I think very cool yeah
we'll definitely come to those cool
great it's been a real pleasure and yeah
I look forward to the part two and
seeing where this conversation leads
next I'm sure will be all both of us
will be kind of interviewing whoever the
next people to surface in this evolving
conversation wherever they come from
yeah yeah thanks guys has been really
enjoyable yeah there's been great
[Music]
you